Guide to the F. Herbert Bormann Papers
Yale University. Department of Manuscripts and Archives
F. Herbert Bormann papers
1950-2009
MS 2012
Yale University. Department of Manuscripts and Archives
6.5
(18 boxes)
The papers document the professional work of ecologist F. Herbert Bormann. The bulk of the papers comprise research materials, speeches, and writings. Research materials include notes, photographs, and grant reports and proposals. Projects that are the most represented include smaller studies at Hubbard Brook Experimental Forest and the Sandbox project. Speeches and writings include articles for popular magazines and newspapers, book drafts, testimony for legislative bodies, and award acceptance speeches. There are also some non-academic writings. Correspondence included in the collection is mainly with colleagues, including some on specific topics such as tropical forestry and the Hubbard Brook Foundation. There is a small amount of personal correspondence as well. Teaching materials are limited and include some syllabi, course notes and materials for specific courses, and lectures on various topics. The papers cover his work from 1950 to 2009, with much of the collection dating from the mid 1980s to the mid 2000s.
Bormann, F. Herbert, 1922-2012
Arrangement
The papers are arranged in five series: I. Correspondence, 1957-2009. II. Research materials, 1950-2006. III. Teaching materials, 1967-2006. IV. Speeches and writings, 1950-2009. V. Born digital materials, 1984-2006.
Conditions Governing Access
Series I-IV are open for research. Series V, Born digital files, is closed pending further processing.
Original audiovisual materials, as well as preservation and duplicating masters, may not be played. Researchers must consult use copies, or if none exist must pay for a use copy, which is retained by the repository. Researchers wishing to obtain an additional copy of non-commercially produced items for their personal use should consult the ordering reproductions information on the Manuscripts and Archives web site.
Immediate Source of Acquisition
Gift of M. Christine Bormann, 2015.
Biographical / Historical
Frederick Herbert Bormann (who used the name Herb) was born on March 24, 1922, in New York, New York. He initially enrolled at the University of Idaho but left after one semester in order to enlist in the United States Navy when the United States entered World War II. After working as a ship fitter and welder, he was selected for officer candidate school at Princeton University. After World War II, he earned his bachelor's degree in agricultural science from Rutgers University in 1948 and his doctorate in plant ecology from Duke University in 1952. He then worked at Emory University, where he taught botany from 1952 to 1956. He moved on to Dartmouth College in 1956 and assumed the position of Oastler Professor of Forest Ecology at Yale University's School of Forestry and Environmental Studies in 1966, where he remained for the rest of his career.
While at Dartmouth, he would take his classes on field trips to study plant life in White Mountain National Forest. He also conducted research at a hydrologic research site at Hubbard Brook Experimental Forest, opened in 1955. Bormann formed a partnership with Gene E. Likens and Noye Johnson from Dartmouth and Robert Pierce of the United States Forest Service to study a watershed within Hubbard Brook. He continued to travel to Hubbard Brook after he started teaching at Yale. His work on the Hubbard Brook Ecosystem Study and others, as well as research performed by other scientists who came to Hubbard Brook yielded a vast body of knowledge of the functions of ecosystems.
His work with Likens, Johnson, Pierce, and others also brought attention to the damage done by humans on these ecosystems. They studied the effects of clear-cutting, when lumber companies cut down every tree in a set area, on soil and water. This research showed that soil lacked important nutrients, and water levels and water quality decreased in these areas as well. They also studied chemical interactions in the ecosystem. Through this work, they discovered that the precipitation in the area was far more acidic than expected. Bormann and Likens also documented the effects of acidic precipitation on the ecosystem in Hubbard Brook, such as plant damage and fish kills. This work was used in the preparation of the Clean Air Act in 1990, which worked to reduce acid rain. Bormann retired from teaching in 1992, although he did continue to work on research as well as offer seminars and lectures on occasion. One of his later projects was studying traditional methods of caring for lawns and the problems fertilizers posed for the environment. He also was interested in suburbanization's effects on the ecology of an area and bridging public policy and environmental research.
Bormann won many prizes for his work over the years, including the Tyler Prize for Environmental Achievement (which he shared with Likens), the National Wildlife Foundation's National Conservation Achievement Award in Science, and Yale's Aldo Leopold Award, which has only been given to one previous academic. He also was elected to the National Academy of Sciences at age 49, one of the youngest scientists to receive that honor. Bormann died on June 7, 2012. He was survived by his wife, M. Christine Williamson Bormann, four children, and six grandchildren.
Scope and Contents
The papers document the professional work of ecologist F. Herbert Bormann. The bulk of the papers comprise research materials, speeches, and writings. Research materials include notes, photographs, and grant reports and proposals. Projects that are the most represented include smaller studies at Hubbard Brook Experimental Forest and the Sandbox project. Speeches and writings include articles for popular magazines and newspapers, book drafts, testimony for legislative bodies, and award acceptance speeches. There are also some non-academic writings. Correspondence included in the collection is mainly with colleagues, including some on specific topics such as tropical forestry and the Hubbard Brook Foundation. There is a small amount of personal correspondence as well. Teaching materials are limited and include some syllabi, course notes and materials for specific courses, and lectures on various topics. The papers cover his work from 1950 to 2009, with much of the collection dating from the mid 1980s to the mid 2000s.
Ecology; Ecology -- Study and teaching; Acid rain; Biotic communities; Clearcutting; Hubbard Brook Experimental Forest (N.H.); Bormann, F. Herbert, 1922-2012; Likens, Gene E., 1935-; Yale University. School of Forestry and Environmental Studies
- Correspondence, 1957-2009; Series I
  Scope and Contents
  This series comprises professional and correspondence sent to and from Bormann. The series has been subdivided into three sections: general, individuals and organizations, and topical. General correspondence is made up of individuals that Bormann did not correspond with a significant amount and is mostly personal in nature. Individuals and organizations contains information about research in progress, travel arrangements for events, and writing projects. Topical contains correspondence related to specific projects and publications, advocacy Bormann participated in, letters to the editor, and academic recommendations. General correspondence is arranged chronologically while correspondence related to specific individuals and organizations and topics are arranged alphabetically.
  - General, 1957-2008, undated (Box 1, Folder 1-6)
  - Individuals and organizations
    - Aber, John: book outline, 2005 (Box 1, Folder 7)
    - Anko, Boštjan, 1999-2004 (Box 1, Folder 8-9)
    - Asahi, 2003 (Box 1, Folder 10)
    - Bock, Ed, 2006 (Box 1, Folder 11)
    - Bourdeau, Philippe, 1995-2004 (Box 1, Folder 12-13)
    - Burch, William, 2001-06-29 (Box 1, Folder 14)
    - Chinese School of Foresters, 1988 (Box 1, Folder 15)
    - Dochinger, Leon S., 1986-01-15 (Box 1, Folder 16)
    - Fickle, Jim, 2006 (Box 1, Folder 17)
    - George?, 2003-01-08 (Box 1, Folder 18)
    - Gill, Dave, 1999 (Box 1, Folder 19)
    - Harper's Magazine, 2004 (Box 1, Folder 20)
    - Hughes, Jeff, 1995-1996 (Box 1, Folder 21)
    - Jackson, Rob, 2001-2003 (Box 1, Folder 22-23)
    - Keller, Kent: Sandbox, 1994-2004 (Box 1, Folder 24-25)
    - Leah?, 2006 (Box 1, Folder 26)
    - Likens, Gene, 1992-2005 (Box 1, Folder 27)
    - Opie, Jon, 2005-05 (Box 1, Folder 28)
    - Parrotta, John, 1991-1992 (Box 1, Folder 29)
    - Sleeper, David, 2004-2005 (Box 1, Folder 30-31)
    - Speth, Gus, 2001-2002 (Box 1, Folder 32)
    - Swank, Wayne, 2005 (Box 1, Folder 33)
    - Swanson, Ann, 1998-2004 (Box 1, Folder 34)
    - United States Forest Service, 1960-1965 (Box 1, Folder 35)
    - University of Vermont, 2003-2005 (Box 1, Folder 36-37)
    - White, Gilbert, 1983-02-07 (Box 1, Folder 38)
  - Topical
    - Bucket watershed, 1998 (Box 1, Folder 39)
    - Correspondence regarding publications, 1990-1997 (Box 2, Folder 1)
    - "Cotton is King", 2006 (Box 2, Folder 2)
    - Deer Path Farm, 2002 (Box 2, Folder 3)
    - Ethics and the Environment scholarship, 1992 (Box 2, Folder 4)
    - Governance committee, Hubbard Brook Foundation, 2001 (Box 2, Folder 5)
    - History of Yale University's School of Forestry and Environmental Science, 2006-2009 (Box 2, Folder 6-7)
    - Hixon study, 2000-2001 (Box 2, Folder 8)
    - "In Their Own Words" project, 2007-2008 (Box 2, Folder 9-10)
    - Italy-Slovenia, 2001 (Box 2, Folder 11)
    - Lecture series, 1991 (Box 2, Folder 12)
    - New York Times public editor, 2003-2004 (Box 2, Folder 13)
    - Requests for recommendations, 1991-1992 (Box 2, Folder 14)
    - Tropical forestry, 1978 (Box 2, Folder 15)
- Research materials, 1950-2006; Series II
  This series comprises notes and photographs related to field research. Grant proposals and reports are also included in this series as it outlines goals of research and some findings. While there are notes clearly pertaining to specific topics such as the Sandbox projects and Hubbard Brook, the majority of the notes are located in small notebooks and small notepads that are labeled chronologically. Photographs document different research sites, the landscape, plants, and animals of different biomes, and rocks and minerals. A significant number of these photographs are 35 millimeter slides. Folders of these slides are labeled with the name listed on the original slide box; the sleeves housing the slides have further labeling of the photographs' subjects. Grant proposals and reports are mainly for the Andrew W. Mellon Foundation. There are also a few for Yale University and the University of Vermont. Materials are arranged alphabetically.
  - Notes
    - General plan for phenology project, 1988-07-14 (Box 3, Folder 1)
    - Hubbard Brook Research Foundation, 2001 (Box 3, Folder 2)
    - Hubbard Brook Research Foundation, current duties and education and outreach plan, 2006 (Box 3, Folder 3)
    - Hubbard Brook roundtable, 2006-10-13-2006-10-14 (Box 3, Folder 4)
    - Mount Cilley study, 1978-07-22 (Box 3, Folder 5)
    - Notebooks
      - General, 1970-circa 1986, undated (Box 3, Folder 6-10, Box 4, Folder 1-3)
      - Hubbard Brook, 1984-1985 (Box 4, Folder 4)
      - Japan lecture, 2003 (Box 4, Folder 5)
      - Hardwood invasion, 1950-1955 (Box 4, Folder 6)
    - Notes on slides taken on various field trips, Circa 1963-1971 (Box 4, Folder 7)
    - Prairie waterway in Farmington, Minnesota, 1993 (Box 4, Folder 8)
    - Sandbox project
      - Meeting materials and notes, 1992-1994 (Box 4, Folder 9)
      - Research, 1999-2000 (Box 4, Folder 10)
      - Research on nitrogen fixation, 1991 (Box 4, Folder 11)
      - Research on weathering, 1993-1994 (Box 5, Folder 1)
      - Research on weathering with data packet, 1994 (Box 5, Folder 2)
    - Taylor, George H.R., Undated (Box 5, Folder 3)
    - Technology and tools, Undated (Box 5, Folder 4)
    - Trips to Hawaii, New Zealand, and Australia, 1990 (Box 5, Folder 5)
    - Trip to Oregon, 1989-09-19 (Box 5, Folder 6)
  - Photographs
    - F. Herbert Bormann and Christine Bormann; logging; Emory- phosphorus transfer; Emory- moisture transfer; cemetery study, dye streaks; lawn sales; Australia; Waterbury, 1960-1994, undated (Box 5, Folder 7)
    - Hubbard Brook soil trench, 1974-1977 (Box 5, Folder 8)
    - Coweeta Hydrologic Laboratory, Circa 1995 (Box 5, Folder 9)
    - Gifford Woods, Moosil Zube from Bob Pierce, Hubbard Brook, Undated (Box 5, Folder 10)
    - Golf course under construction in a northern hardwood forest in Campton, New Hampshire; Powerline Brook, 1997 (Box 5, Folder 11)
    - Old field; trachyte, limestone, granite (Nova Scotia paper); nylon net in operation; aerial photographs (Hubbard Brook); ecology, Undated (Box 5, Folder 12)
    - Research team, 1971-1987 (Box 5, Folder 13)
    - Root grafts, prints and negatives, Circa 1958 (Box 5, Folder 14)
    - Root graft study, selection of tress, Undated (Box 5, Folder 15)
    - Slides
      - General, 1985-1999 (Box 5, Folder 16)
      - Acid rain, Sandbox, travels, forest fires, 1976-1988 (Box 6, Folder 1-2)
      - Alaska, grassland, desert, 1960-1972 (Box 6, Folder 3-5)
      - Biology, insects, erosion, 175A, 1962-1997 (Box 7, Folder 1-2)
      - Boreal tropical forest, 1964-1978, undated (Box 7, Folder 3-4)
      - Branford Supply Pond, 1996-04 (Box 7, Folder 5)
      - China and Hong Kong, 1985 (Box 7, Folder 6, Box 8, Folder 1)
      - Deciduous forest, 1948-1987 (Box 8, Folder 2-3)
      - Hubbard Brook, 1953-1989 (Box 8, Folder 4-6, Box 9, Folder 1)
      - Sandbox project, nitrogen storage and fixation, Circa 1991 (Box 9, Folder 2)
      - Talks, pin cherry, cloud water; Hubbard Brook; model of ecosystem decline; ozone populus; bioscience, 1984-1987 (Box 9, Folder 3)
    - Supply pond, Circa 1990s (Box 9, Folder 4)
    - Unidentified plant, Undated (Box 9, Folder 5)
    - Unknown photographs and negatives, 1996-1999 (Box 9, Folder 6)
  - Grant reports and proposals
    - General proposals, 1957-1993 (Box 9, Folder 7)
    - Budget requests to the Andrew W. Mellon Foundation, 1996-1999 (Box 9, Folder 8-9)
    - Cooperative agreement for studies on ecosystem processes between Yale University School of Forestry and Environmental Studies and School of Natural Resources, University of Vermont, 1992-2002 (Box 9, Folder 10-11)
    - Correspondence with the Andrew W. Mellon foundation, 1993-08-11 (Box 9, Folder 12)
    - Proposal for support from the Andrew W. Mellon Foundation, 1986-1994 (Box 9, Folder 13, Box 10, Folder 1)
    - Report to the Andrew W. Mellon Foundation with publications related to the Sandbox studies, 1996-1998, 1998-1999 (Box 10, Folder 2)
    - Proposal to the Santa Barbara County Resource Management Department, 1993 (Box 10, Folder 3)
    - Proposals to the United States Department of Agriculture and the Environmental Protection Agency, 1993-1994 (Box 10, Folder 4)
    - Proposals to Yale University, 1967, 2006 (Box 10, Folder 5)
- Teaching materials, 1967-2006; Series III
  This series comprises notes, outlines, syllabi and other materials for courses and lectures Bormann gave. Almost all of these courses and lectures were given at Yale University's School of Forestry and Environmental Studies. The series is arranged alphabetically.
  - Benoit-Balmori course, 2001-2003 (Box 11, Folder 1)
  - Course notes
    - Aquatic ecology and suburbanization, 2002 (Box 11, Folder 2)
    - Patterns and processes in terrestrial ecosystems, 1968-1972 (Box 11, Folder 3-4)
    - Seminar in ecosystem ecology, 1986-1992 (Box 11, Folder 5-7)
    - Suburb hydrologic cycle, 2000 (Box 11, Folder 8)
    - Succession, Circa 1960s (Box 11, Folder 9, Box 12, Folder 1-2)
  - Course outlines
    - The home as ecosystem, 1976 (Box 12, Folder 3)
    - Supply pond, 2000-2002 (Box 12, Folder 4)
  - Ecology and ecosystems materials, 1998-2006 (Box 12, Folder 5)
  - Guide to human in disgression slide notes, Undated (Box 12, Folder 6)
  - Lecture ideas, Circa 1992 (Box 12, Folder 7)
  - Lecture series on grazing
    - General, 1993-1995 (Box 12, Folder 8)
    - Arid and semiarid west- grazing cost, 1993-circa 1995 (Box 12, Folder 9)
    - Background, planning, and sources, Circa 1993-circa 1995 (Box 12, Folder 10)
    - Bibliography, 1993 (Box 12, Folder 11)
    - Potential lecturers, 1993-1994 (Box 12, Folder 12)
  - Shellfish, 2004 (Box 12, Folder 13)
  - Syllabi: pattern and process in terrestrial ecology, ecosystemology; structure and function of ecosystems, 1967-1971 (Box 12, Folder 14)
  - Syllabus and midterm exam, seminar in ecosystem ecology, Undated (Box 12, Folder 15)
- Speeches and writings, 1950-2009; Series IV
  This series comprises various speeches and writings composed by Bormann. The majority of the speeches were given to scientific and professional organizations and are related to his research at Hubbard Brook or environmentalism and ecology in general. Other speeches include award acceptance speeches, commencement speeches, and special/keynote speeches given at lectures, seminars, and symposiums. Much of the writings in this series are on general ecology topics for popular magazines and newspapers. Other works include drafts and edits of his book Redesigning the American Lawn and other writings on freedom lawns, testimony before legislative bodies on different environmental concerns, and a small amount of academic papers, including those that had collaborating parties. Materials are arranged alphabetically.
  - General
    This section contains both speeches and writings that Bormann prepared on the same topics for different venues and media outlets.
    - Global environmental debt
      - Ecomythology, Circa 1993-circa 1994 (Box 13, Folder 1)
        General
        See also Global environmental debt and ecomythology.
      - References, Circa 1998-2002 (Box 13, Folder 2)
      - Various versions, 1990-2002 (Box 13, Folder 3)
    - Home as an ecosystem, 1976 (Box 13, Folder 4)
    - Hubbard Brook, 1985-1996 (Box 13, Folder 5)
  - Speeches
    - General, 1972-2004 (Box 13, Folder 6-8)
    - "Air Pollution Stress on Forests: Decision Making in an Uncertain Environment" (Green Chair Lecture Series), 1987-12-02; 1 (Box 17)
      Conditions Governing Access
      Original audiovisual materials, as well as preservation and duplicating masters, may not be played. Researchers must consult use copies, or if none exist must pay for a use copy, which is retained by the repository. Researchers wishing to obtain an additional copy of non-commercially produced items for their personal use should consult the ordering reproductions information on the Manuscripts and Archives web site.
    - Allegheny College, 1992 (Box 13, Folder 9)
    - American lawn, Sarah Lawrence College, 1995-02-16 (Box 13, Folder 10)
    - Award acceptances, 1993-1994 (Box 13, Folder 11)
    - Blue Planet Award
      - Introductory remarks, 2003 (Box 13, Folder 12)
      - Prize acceptance, 2003 (Box 13, Folder 13)
      - Commemorative lecture, 2003 (Box 13, Folder 14)
    - Connecticut Historic Trust Conference, Undated (Box 13, Folder 15)
    - Duke University, 1988- (Box 13, Folder 16)
    - "The Ecology of Tropical Forests Ecosystems, 2000 (Box 13, Folder 17)
    - Environmental science and landscape policy; ecosystem regulation, 1998 (Box 13, Folder 18)
    - 50th anniversary of the Hubbard Brook Experimental Forest, 2005 (Box 13, Folder 19)
    - Hubbard Brook, Circa 1988 (Box 13, Folder 20)
    - "Hubbard Brook Experimental Forest", 1983-12; 1 (Box 18)
    - Lectures, seminars, and symposiums, 1984-1999 (Box 13, Folder 21)
    - National Convention of Congregational Churches, Undated (Box 13, Folder 22)
    - Nature Conservancy, 1969-05 (Box 13, Folder 23)
    - New Hampshire Science Center talk, 2004 (Box 13, Folder 24)
    - Nuclear war, 1962 (Box 13, Folder 25)
    - "The Origin of the Hubbard Brook Ecosystem Study", 2004-07 (Box 13, Folder 26)
    - "The Origin of the Small Watershed Technique", 1997-2003 (Box 13, Folder 27)
    - Personal speeches, 1993-2008 (Box 14, Folder 1)
    - Recovery and future of the northeastern forest, 1996 (Box 14, Folder 2)
    - Santa Barbara Botanic Garden talk, 2005-2006 (Box 14, Folder 3)
    - Slide for Taiwan, 1996 (Box 14, Folder 4)
    - Suburbanization and the hydrologic cycle, 2002 (Box 14, Folder 5)
    - Talk on protection of nature, Undated (Box 14, Folder 6)
    - University of Vermont commencement address, 2005 (Box 14, Folder 7)
    - University of Vermont lectures, 2000, undated (Box 14, Folder 8)
    - "Yale Reports", 1970-04-12 (Box 14, Folder 9)
  - Writings
    - General, 1990-2005 (Box 14, Folder 10-13)
    - Administrative outlines and reports, Undated (Box 14, Folder 14)
    - Assisi paper, "The Global Environmental Deficit- a Useful Concept for Earth Keepers", 1992-1994 (Box 14, Folder 15)
    - Biomass scatter plots for unknown paper, 1991 (Box 14, Folder 16)
    - Bormann's autobiography, 2002-2006 (Box 14, Folder 17-18)
    - Bormann's biographical notes, 2002-08 (Box 14, Folder 19)
    - Brazil report, 1986-11-09-1986-11-19 (Box 14, Folder 20)
    - Brown, Lester, 1981-1982 (Box 14, Folder 21)
    - "Clear-Cutting, Experiment and Practice", Circa 1990 (Box 14, Folder 22)
    - Collaborations with researchers from the University of Vermont, 1992-1993 (Box 14, Folder 23, Box 15, Folder 1)
    - Conservation of ecosystems and conservation of fossil fuels, Undated (Box 15, Folder 2)
    - "Confronting the Environmental Debt", 1997-2004 (Box 15, Folder 3)
    - "Confronting the Global Environmental Deficit", 1993-1994 (Box 15, Folder 4)
    - "Confronting the Global Environmental Deficit," references, 1993 (Box 15, Folder 5)
    - Drafting notes, Undated (Box 15, Folder 6)
    - Drafts and outlines, Undated (Box 15, Folder 7)
    - Earth Day, 2007-2008, undated (Box 15, Folder 8)
    - "The Ecological Choice- Harmony or Chaos", Undated (Box 15, Folder 9)
    - Ecological services drafting, 2000 (Box 15, Folder 10)
    - Edits and critiques, 2003-2004 (Box 15, Folder 11)
    - Environment and political policy, 2006 (Box 15, Folder 12)
    - Freedom Lawns
      - Meeting, 1998-11-04 (Box 15, Folder 13)
      - Notes by Sally Atkins, 1998-12-21 (Box 15, Folder 14)
      - Research questionnaires, 1998 (Box 15, Folder 15)
    - Gas prices
      - "Gas Prices and Land Abandonment", 2006-04 (Box 15, Folder 16)
      - Gas prices and landscape, 2005 (Box 15, Folder 17-18)
    - Global environmental debt and ecomythology, 1995-1996 (Box 15, Folder 19)
      See also Ecomythology.
    - Golf courses, 1996-1998 (Box 15, Folder 20)
    - Golf courses, correspondence, 1998-11-19 (Box 15, Folder 21)
    - Green governance and environmental debt, 2002-2003 (Box 15, Folder 22)
    - History of the School of Forestry and Environmental Studies, 2009 (Box 15, Folder 23)
    - Hubbard Brook
      - General, 1997-2004 (Box 15, Folder 24)
      - "Hubbard Brook Marks 25 Years of Visionary Ecosystem Research", Undated (Box 15, Folder 25)
      - Hubbard Brook poster, 2006 (Box 15, Folder 26)
    - Hydrologic studies, 2004 (Box 15, Folder 27)
    - Intelligent design, 2005 (Box 15, Folder 28)
    - "Investigating Dynamic Functions and Complex Legacies in Watershed Ecosystems", 2003 (Box 15, Folder 29)
    - Johnson, Chris, et al. "Whole Tree Harvesting Effects on Soil Chemical Properties in a Northern Hardwood Forest", Undated (Box 15, Folder 30)
    - "Lesson from Hubbard Brook", Circa 1984 (Box 16, Folder 1)
    - "Losing Contact with Nature", 2008 (Box 16, Folder 2)
    - "Man's Mastery Over Nature" draft, Undated (Box 16, Folder 3)
    - "The Marriage of Ecology and Agriculture: an Ecologist's Perspective", 1989 (Box 16, Folder 4)
    - New York Botanical Garden Forest, 1997-08-11 (Box 16, Folder 5)